Arthur P. Gorman Papers
Arthur P. Gorman Papers
1804-1935
Gorman, Arthur P. (Arthur Pue), 1839-1906.
3.0 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Senator from Maryland, 1881-1889 and 1903-1906. Collection includes correspondence (1838-1935); newspaper clippings (1884-1906); pamphlets, speech notes, Congressional printed material, and legal documents relating to Gorman's political career. Correspondents include Henry G. Davis and Thomas G. Hayes.
149017
Biographical History
Arthur Pue Gorman (1839-1906) was a United States Senator from Maryland. Beginning as a page in the House of Representatives (1852), he was transferred to the Senate through the influence of Illinois senator Stephen A. Douglas, who made him his private secretary. Gorman subsequently served the Senate as page, messenger, assistant doorkeeper, assistant postmaster, and finally postmaster. In September of 1866, Gorman was appointed collector of internal revenue for the fifth district of Maryland, and he served as director and later as president of the Chesapeake Ohio Canal Co.
Gorman served in the Maryland House of Delegates from 1869 to 1875, with one session as speaker of the house. He served in the Maryland State Senate (1875-1881) and then in the United States Senate (1881-1899 and 1902-1906), where he soon became a leader of the conservative wing of his party (the "Bourbon Democrats"). During his congressional tenure he was the Democratic caucus chairman (1890-1898), chairman of the Senate Committee on Printing, and a member of the Senate Committee on Private Land Claims. He played a major role in financial and tariff legislation, especially the Wilson-Gorman Tariff of 1894.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Arthur P. Gorman Papers consist of Correspondence-subject files (1838-1935); Cpeeches; and Memorabilia.
Correspondence-subject files includes letters with family, politicians and business people (most notably with railroad executives). A list of the names of correspondents who have not been given unique folders was created in an earlier arrangement of this collection. It is included and has been anotated to indicate in which folder letters from each person are now filed.
Speeches contains printed text as well as notes and fragments. Speeches given by Senator Gorman on the floor of the Senate are filed with other legislative material from the session of Congress during which they were delivered.
Memorabilia includes extensive clippings, personal financial records, copies of newspaper editorials, printed material, a set of weekly banking circulars, Postmaster's bonds miscellaneous documents and souvenirs.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically. Speeches are arranged alphabetically by title or subject except for Senator Gorman's speeches on the floor of the Senate which are included with other legislative material from the session of Congress during which they were delivered. Memorabilia is arranged by type of material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Gorman, Arthur P. (Arthur Pue), 1839-1906.; Ammen, Daniel, 1820-1898.; Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898.; Belmont, August, 1813-1890.; Berret, James G. (James Gabriel), 1815-1901.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Butler, M. C. (Matthew Calbraith) 1836-1909.; Carroll, John Lee, 1830-1911.; Chaille-Long, C. (Charles), 1842-1917.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Cole, William H. (William Hinson), 1837-1886.; Crisfield, John W. (John Woodland), 1806-1897.; Crisp, Charles F. (Charles Frederick), 1845-1896.; Cullom, Shelby M. (Shelby Moore), 1829-1914.; Davis, Henry Gassaway, 1823-1916.; Dimmick, Mary Scott Lord, 1858-1948.; Douglas, Henry Kyd, 1838-1903.; Frémont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902.; Gibson, Charles H. (Charles Hopper), 1842-1900.; Groome, James Black, 1838-1893.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901.; Hayes, Thomas G. (Thomas Gordon), 1844-; Howell, Evan P. (Evan Park), 1839-1905.; Jones, James K. (James Kimbrough), 1839-1908.; Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905.; Lapham, Elbridge Gerry, 1814-1890.; Latrobe, Ferdinand Claiborne, 1833-1911.; Maddox, John W., 1848-1922.; Moltke, Helmuth, Graf von, 1800-1891.; Murphy, Jeremiah Henry, 1835-1893.; Parsons, William Henry, 1826-1907.; Randall, Samuel J. (Samuel Jackson), 1828-1890.; Ransom, Matt W. (Matt Whitaker), 1826-1904.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1835-1914.; Vance, Zebulon Baird, 1830-1894.; Warner, A. J. (Adoniram Judson), 1834-1910.; Webster, Edwin H. (Edwin Hanson), 1829-1893.; Democratic Party (Md.); Democratic Party (U.S.); United States. -- Congress (49th: 1885-1887); United States. -- Congress (50th: 1887-1889); United States. -- Congress (51st: 1889-1891); United States. -- Congress (52nd: 1891-1893); United States. -- Congress (53rd: 1893-1895); United States. -- Congress (54th: 1895-1897); United States. -- Congress (55th: 1897-1899); United States. -- Congress (58th: 1903-1905); Legislators -- Maryland.; Legislators -- United States.; Patronage, political -- United States.; Silver question (1886); Baltimore (Md.) -- Politics and government.; Maryland -- Politics and government, 1865-1950.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Speeches (documents); Legislators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchases, 1964-1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Biographical material and list of minor names (Box 1)
  - Adee, Avery Augustus, See Sympathy letters after house fire.
  - Ammen, Daniel, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Applegarth, William F., 1892 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, William H., Jr., See Merchants' National Bank Baltimore, Md.
  - Baltimore, MD, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, 1885-1901 (Box 1)
  - Baughman, L. Victor, 1888-1890; 1906 (Box 1)
  - Bayard, Thomas Francis, See Congratulatory letters;Sympathy letters after house fire.
  - Belmont, August, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Berret, James Gabriel, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Bird, William Edgar, 1868-1872 (Box 1)
  - Bowlus, Noah, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Brattan, Joseph Yancy, See Baltimore and Ohio Railroad.
  - Brewer, James R., See Sympathy letters after house fire.
  - Bryan, Olin, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Bryan, William Jennings, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, James, 1857 (Box 1)
  - Burgess, Richard, See Buchanan, James.
  - Butler, Isaac, 1834; 1862 (Box 1)
  - Butler, Matthew Calbraith, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Cameron, Margaret Campbell, undated (Box 1)
  - Carroll, John Lee, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Carroll, Mrs Charles A., See Nursery and Child's Hospital Baltimore.
  - Carson, John Miller, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Cator, Robinson W., See Merchant's National Bank Baltimore.
  - Chaille-Long, Charles, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Company, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, 1904 (Box 1)
  - Clarke, James C., See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill;Job seekers;Miscellaneous.
  - Cleaver, T. J., See Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Company.
  - Cleveland, Grover, 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - Cole, William Hinson, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory letters B-W (Box 1)
  - Coyle, Andrew McNair, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Crisfield, J. W., 1862 (Box 1)
  - Crisp, Charles Frederick, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Cullom, Shelby Moore, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Henry Gassaway, See West Virginia Central Railroad Company.
  - Davis, John W., See Baltimore and Ohio Railroad.
  - Democratic National Committee, 1885; 1892,; 1896 (Box 1)
  - Democratic Party of Maryland, 1885-1887 (Box 1)
  - Dimmick, Mary Scott, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Douglas, Henry Kyd, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Edge, Camilla Sewall, undated (Box 1)
  - Foster, J. Nelson, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Frémont, Jessie Benton, undated (Box 1)
  - Gambill, William Gorman, 1885; 1899 (Box 1)
  - Gans, Daniel, See Sympathy letters after house fire; Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Getty, William Reed, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Gibson, Charles Hopper, undated (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Arthur P., Jr., 1907 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Charles Edward, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Elizabeth A., 1885 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Hannah ("Hattie"), 1897; 1905 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Peter Calhoun, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, William Henry, 1890 (Box 1)
  - Groome, James Black, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Gwinn, Charles J. M., 1890; 1892,; 1896 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Benjamin, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Thomas Gordon, 1892-1894 (Box 1)
  - The Holton-Arms School, 1918-1920 (Box 1)
  - Hopkins, Louis N., 1892; 1894,; 1895 (Box 1)
  - Howell, Evan P., 1892 (Box 1)
  - Inman, John H., 1894 (Box 1)
  - Job seekers B-E (Box 2)
  - Job seekers F-L (Box 2)
  - Job seekers M-W (Box 2)
  - Jones, James Kimbrough, undated (Box 2)
  - Jones, John M., See Sympathy letters after house fire.
  - Journal of Industry Quincy, Il, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Joyce, E.T., See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Kelton, John Cunningham, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Kenna, John Edward, See United States Senate: 49th Congress.
  - Knights of Labor, 1896; 1897 (Box 2)
  - Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1885; 1893 (Box 2)
  - Lanahan, Thomas M., 1885 (Box 2)
  - Langley, Samuel Pierpont, undated (Box 2)
  - Lapham, Elbridge G., 1885 (Box 2)
  - Latrobe, Ferdinand Claiborne, 1885; 1890 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Guy Carleton, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Lee, James Fenner, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Leinweber, Christian, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Leroux, Jules, 1884-1885 (Box 2)
  - Lloyd, Henry, 1885 (Box 2)
  - London, John James, 1803 (Box 2)
  - Lowndes, Lloyd, 1883; 1885,; 1887 (Box 2)
  - Maddox, John W., 1886 (Box 2)
  - Maddox, Joseph H., 1878 (Box 2)
  - Maryland Democratic Club of Washington, D. C., 1887 (Box 2)
  - McSherry, James, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Merchants' National Bank Baltimore, MD, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Meredith, Gilmore, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Joseph S., 1885 (Box 2)
  - Moltke, Helmuth Johann Ludwig von, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Murphy, Jeremiah Henry, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Nimmo, Joseph, 1889 (Box 2)
  - The Nursery and Child's Hospital Baltimore, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Order of the American Union, 1884-1885 (Box 2)
  - The Orpheus Club, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Ousley, Clarence, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Parsons, William Henry, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Petitions, 1894, undated (Box 2)
  - Pilgrims of the United States, 1903-1904 (Box 2)
  - Quinn, John, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Randall, James Ryder, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Randall, Samuel Jackson, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Randle, Arthur E., 1899 (Box 2)
  - Ransom, Matt Whitaker, 1898 (box 2)
  - Rasin, Isaac Freeman, 1892; 1893,; 1896 (Box 2)
  - Scharf, John Thomas, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Seventh Ward Democratic Association of Baltimore, 1892 (Box 3)
  - Sewall, Arthur, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Sherman, John, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Sinclair, Arthur, Jr., 1838 (Box 3)
  - Smith, Willoughby N., See Baltimore and Ohio Railroad.
  - Sons of the American Revolution, 1907 (Box 3)
  - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Stewart, Annie E. Foote (Mrs. William Morris Stewart), undated (Box 3)
  - Stone, William J., 1899 (Box 3)
  - Straus, Oscar Solomon, 1884 (Box 3)
  - Stubbs, Daniel W., See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Stump, Henry Arthur, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Sympathy letters after house fire, 1890 (Box 3)
  - Tammany Society, 1886 (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Fred P., See Journal of Industry.
  - Townsend, George Alfred, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Treasury Department, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Tubman, S. Magruder, 1879; 1885 (Box 3)
  - United Sons of the Republic, 1885; 1889 (Box 3)
  - United States Internal Revenue, 1887 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 49th Congress, 1885-1887 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 50th Congress, 1887-1889 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 51st Congress, 1889-1891 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 52nd Congress, 1891-1893 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 53rd Congress, 1893-1895 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 54th Congress, 1895-1897 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate: 55th Congress, 1897-1899 (Box 4)
  - United States Senate: 58th Congress, 1903-1905 (Box 4)
  - United States Senate: Joint Committee on Printing, 1891 (Box 4)
  - United States Senate Library, 1896 (Box 4)
  - United States Senate Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
  - Vance, Zebulon Baird, undated (Box 4)
  - Wall, Edward Clarence, 1899 (Box 4)
  - Warner, Adoniram Judson, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Webster, Edwin H., 1863 (Box 4)
  - Wellman, Walter E., 1898 (Box 4)
  - West Virginia Central Railway Company, 1888 (Box 4)
  - Willcox, Orlando B., 1882 (Box 4)
  - Williams, Francis Churchill, undated (Box 4)
  - Williams, John Cassel, undated (Box 4)
  - Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill, 1894 (Box 4)
  - Winchester and Potomac Railroad Company, 1888 (Box 4)
  - Windom, William, 1891 (Box 4)
  - Wood, William Patrick, 1885 (Box 4)
  - World's Fair: Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Yerkes, Harman, See Wilson-Gorman Tariff Bill.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence A-W (Box 4)
- Speeches
  - Civil Service reform, 1885 (Box 5)
  - Land Ownership in Great Britain, 1896 (Box 5)
  - Outrages of Yesterday, 1886 (Box 5)
  - Senator Gorman on Silver, 1896 (Box 5)
  - Notes and fragments, 1891-1896 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings
    - Clippings, 1884 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1885 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1886 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1887 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1888 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1889 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1890 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1891 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1892 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1893 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1894 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1895 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1896; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1897 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1897; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1898 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1899 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1900 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1901 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1904 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1905 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1906 (Box 6)
  - Financial records, 1833-1896 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper editorials, typescript and holograph copies, 1888-1896 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6)
  - Printed material
    - Senator Gorman Viewed by His Friends and Enemies, 1897 (Box 6)
    - The Verdict February 12, 1900 (Box 6)
    - Weekly banking circulars, 1891-1899 (Box 6)
  - Postmaster's bonds, 1804-1849 (Box 6)
  - Quotations, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)